<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>JPtacek.com | Musings on code and who knows what 3ls3</title>
    <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/feed/" rel="self"/>
    <link href="https://www.jptacek.com"/>
    <updated>2016-08-16T15:02:37.151Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.jptacek.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name>John Ptacek</name>
        <email>jptacek@gmail.com</email>
    </author>

    
    <entry>
        <title>Angular/Angular2 Introduction</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/08/Anuglar2Introduction/"/>
        <updated>2016-08-12T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2016-08-12,/2016/08/Anuglar2Introduction/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spent a lot of time blogging about <a href="https://jptacek.com/tags/angularjs/">AngularJS</a> in the past. Time moves on, especially on the Internet and 
<a href="https://www.google.com">Google</a> is feverishly working on finishing up <a href="https://angular.io">Angular2</a>, which is currently in release candidate as of 
this writing (August of 2016).
<img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/08/Anuglar2Introduction/angularLogo.svg?raw=true" width="25%"></p>
<p>We will take a similar approach to last time, where we developed a periodic table application that investigates different features about 
Angular.</p>
<p>One thing to note, Google has renamed Angular 2. The previous version of AngularJS, the 1.x stack was called AngularJS. The new
version is now called just Angular. Part of the reason for this is to show its ability to create native mobile applications, so 
the JavaScript name can be a bit limiting. We will, in general, keep the same names. Angular and/or Angular 2 will refere to the current 
verison of Anuglar. The older versions will be called AngularJS or Angular 1.x.</p>
<p>First though, why even upgrade at all, since the upgrade path from Angular 1.x to Angular 2? Lets highlight some reasons.</p>
<h3 id="component-based">Component Based</h3>
<p>Web development is moving towards component based development, especially with some of the emerging
<a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/NOTE-HTMLComponents">web standards</a>. While those standards are not fully completed yet, Google is definitley
preparing for that world. If you need further proof, checkout Google&#39;s <a href="https://www.polymer-project.org/1.0/">Polymer</a> project.</p>
<h3 id="typescript">TypeScript</h3>
<p>TypeScript is an extension of JavaScript created by Microsoft, open sourced and adopted by Google (I know!! Right?!?!)
TypeScript essentially is ECMAScript 6, combined with the ability to create type and annotations. It is used to create 
Angular. The code samples developed by Google are all in TypeScript, with JavaScipt following later. You don&#39;t HAVE to use 
TypeScript, but it will make life easier.</p>
<h3 id="virtual-dom">Virtual DOM</h3>
<p>One of the things <a href="https://facebook.github.io/react/">ReactJS</a> taught the world, is the value of a Virtual DOM. This is a virtual representation
of the Document Object Model (DOM) for a HTML page. You can then work on this in memory which offers GREAT performance improvements. 
Google has adopted a Virtual DOM and has realized the expected performance boosts.</p>
<p>Those are a few of the highlights of why Angular2 over AngularJS 1.x. We will hit more as we contineu our series.</p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2016/08/Anuglar2Introduction/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>That Conference 2016 - Angular vs React</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/08/ThatConference2016/"/>
        <updated>2016-08-11T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2016-08-11,/2016/08/ThatConference2016/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my favorite things each year is <a href="https://www.thatconference.com">That Conference</a>. I have been lucky enough to 
be chosen as a speaker each year (though I missed last year due to work commitments).</p>
<p>This year I talked on Angular vs React, and compared two of the most popular things going on in the world of 
JavaScript these days. Thanks to all of those who attended and provided engaging converstation.</p>
<p>For those interested, here is the <a href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/08/ThatConference2016/./Angular vs React-Talk.pptx">presentation</a>. I will also be uploading the code to my 
<a href="https://wwww.github.com/jptacek">GitHub</a> in a while after I button it up some more.</p>
<p>Thanks to all the organizer, sponsors and speakers for a great community event! I highly encourage folks to go 
next year, Aug 7-9.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/08/ThatConference2016/ThatConference2016.jpg" alt="ThatConference 2016"></p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2016/08/ThatConference2016/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Apple WWDC 2016 Recap</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/07/WWDC2016Recap/"/>
        <updated>2016-07-05T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2016-07-05,/2016/07/WWDC2016Recap/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Developer world, there are usually three big conferences each year; Microsoft’s Build, Google I/O and Apple’s World Wide Developer Conference (WWDC). Google’s <a href="https://events.google.com/io2016/">I/O</a> conference, its 10th, just wrapped up last week. Let us take a spin around some of the more interesting announcements from the conference. We have previously looked at 
<a href="https://jptacek.com/2016/04/Build2016Recap/">Build</a> and <a href="https://jptacek.com/2016/05/GoogleIO2016Recap/">Google I/O</a>, lets
dive into <a href="https://developer.apple.com/wwdc/">WWDC</a> which was held in June in San Francisco.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/07/WWDC2016Recap/wwdc2016.jpg" alt="Apple WWDC 2016"> </p>
<p>Apple’s WWDC keynote this year, tended to be the more consumer facing, rather than developer facing of the other keynotes from 2016. A majority of the time was spent on items such as iOS 10 features, Apple music redesign, Apple photos, etc. </p>
<p><strong>Siri</strong> – One of the big rumors heading into WWDC was that iMessage, Apple’s very popular messaging platform would be being made available to Android devices. That wasn’t announced. However, a slew of changes are coming to iMessage. The changes mostly are “fun”; items such as stickers, new emojis, videos, bubble effects etc. Given the popularity of iMessage though, we know these features will be popular. Unlike other messaging application, for example Facebook messenger, WhatsApp, etc, the usage may be limited, since as of now, you cannot take advantage of these new features for users on other platforms like Android. Given that for most iOS users iMessage means SMS, it could lead to frustration.</p>
<p><strong>iMessage</strong> – here have been two OS releases of Apple Watch in its first year. However, it can still be frustratingly slow to use in day to day activities. Apple announced watchOS 3 which seems to greatly alleviate some of the performance issues. Applications were shown on the current version and the new version and were markedly faster. Apple Watch users will be excited for the new upgrade if those performance gains are realized as promised.</p>
<p><strong>Apple Watch</strong> – Google announced their me too competitor to Amazon’s Alexa, a voice activated search appliance for the home. You will be able to ask Google Home things like what is the weather for the day, did the Chicago Fire win last night, etc. Pricing and availability dates were not announced. Google’s introduction video.</p>
<p><strong>iOS</strong> – iOS has a new round of updates as it hits version 10. The notification screen has been greatly redesigned. Apple music has been streamlined and the maps application has been improved. 3D touch, which was introduced with last year’s new iPhones (6s, 6s Plus) is also more fully integrated into the system, especially on the notification screen.</p>
<p><strong>Contextual Awareness</strong> – The interesting thing that is permeating a lot of the developer conversations as of late is contextual awareness. A platform, like Google Now, can read email, look at your calendar and contacts as well as location to provide a wealth of information. This can provide very useful and pertinent information to a user. However, the downside to this is you are giving up a some of your privacy, as the service collects your information and mines it. This has definitely been Google’s approach. Apple has a stated focus on privacy, so it is exceedingly more difficult for them to provide these kind of services, which often rely on cloud computing because the information would need to leave the phone. So contextual awareness happens within an application, like Siri, where it will be much more limited.</p>
<p>At WWDC, to make iOS more successful at providing contextual awareness, Apple introduced differential privacy. It is all a bit murky, and involves some crazy abstract mathematics, but it essentially takes information from your phone, randomizes it a bit to mask individual information, stores it and then can aggregate the information together. </p>
<p>How this actually works in the real world, remains to be seen. However, at first glance, I cannot imagine it being very successful, because the data that would be helpful to you, for example, discerning information about an upcoming flight, wouldn’t have enough other randomized data elements in the cloud for iOS to be able to find information about the flight. </p>
<p>Resultantly, Apple is using this new feature in four areas for iOS; emoji replacement in iMessage, predictive text in iMessage, search in Notes and search in Spotlight.</p>
<p>It is an interesting take at trying to be contextual and protect user privacy, I am just not sure how successful Apple will be trying to provide contextual awareness with it in their platform as they compete against happily data mining competitors such as Facebook and Google.</p>
<p>So that is a quick tour of 2016 WWDC. Not a lot of big announcements, but more of a refining. As phone platforms reach platform maturity, there will be less and less groundbreaking enhancements on the phone. A lot of the interesting things will be happening in the cloud services that drive these devices. Apple has a lot of catching up to do here.</p>
<p>This blog post originally appeared at <a href="https://www.skylinetechnologies.com/Insights/Skyline-Blog/July_2016/Apple_WWDC_2016_Recap">Skyline Technologies</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2016/07/WWDC2016Recap/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>What is Quantum Computing?</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/06/WhatIsQuantumComputing/"/>
        <updated>2016-06-27T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2016-06-27,/2016/06/WhatIsQuantumComputing/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Quantum computers hold the promise of massive increases in computational speed for certain classes of problems. However, what quantum computers are and how they work can be a bit of a mystery, mostly because quantum physics is a mystery. We are going to dive in and find out how they work.</p>
<p>First, a little bit about quantum physics. At the turn of the century, physicists were a pretty confident lot. Maxwell had described electromagnetism with Maxwell’s equations and most problems appeared to be solve. However, a couple of items persisted that could not be described by “classical” physics, such as blackbody radiation or the photoelectric effect. It is safe to say, understanding these phenomena and the discovery of Quantum Mechanics was the accomplishment of the 20th century.</p>
<p>Quantum Mechanics describes the physical world at the size of the atom, at which point, the classical laws of Newton and Maxwell fall apart. One of the main takeaways, especially for Quantum Computing, is the idea that NOTHING is specific at the quantum level. Particles, such as electrons, at the quantum level exists in states; aka their position, speed and energy. They may be low energy, they may be high energy, but knowing these states is not always doable unless we measure them. You may know a probability for the energy of an electron, but not the exact value. Schrödinger’s Equation, which describes the probability of an electron being in any state, not exactness. So while the laws of Newton allowed us to put a person on the moon with great accuracy, the laws at the quantum level just tell us probabilities. It is more feelings than certainty!</p>
<p>Schrödinger’s Equations lead us to one of the key components of Quantum Computing, and that is superposition. One of the outcomes of Schrodinger’s Equation, is that any valid quantum states can be added together to create another valid quantum state. Another way of saying this, there are many valid solutions at any given time, and ALL solutions are valid. In the physical world, observing what the answer is, chooses one of those valid solutions. It is a lot to get one’s head around.</p>
<p>To illustrate the madness of what we are talking about, consider the famous example of Schrödinger’s Cat, a thought experiment in physics. The version I have heard, is you put a cat in a box with a radioactive isotope that has a 50% chance of decaying in a minute. If the particle decays within a minute, the cat dies, if it doesn’t the cat lives. With quantum physics, the craziness comes is that you have no way of knowing if the cat is alive or dead, it exists in both states. This is superposition. There are two valid solutions to the equation, the possible states for the cat are alive or dead. However, superposition states that any solution can be added together and that is also a valid solution, so the cat is also alive and dead. It isn’t until we observe, that one of the states is chosen. If you really want to have your mind blown, check out this YouTube video describing <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IOYyCHGWJq4">Schrödinger’s Cat</a>.</p>
<p>So if we think of our current computers and transistors, they are based on the idea of a bit; either on or off or 0 and 1. In quantum computing, bits are replaced by quantum bits, or qubits. A qubit can be a 0 or a 1, it can be both a 0 and 1, or any value in between. 
In the current world with bits, only two options exist at any single time, and steps are performed linearly, in the quantum world, with the concept of qubits you can store multiple values at all at once and all the solutions are processes in parallel. Once you determine the state by measuring or observing, you get a single answer.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/06/WhatIsQuantumComputing/Quantum_computer.svg?raw=true" alt="Qubit"> source: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_computing#/media/File:Quantum_computer.svg">Wikipedia</a></p>
<p>In the real world, what does this mean. So far, not a whole lot. You aren’t going to get a tremendous increase in performance playing Minecraft. Quantum Computing has so far been proven to be much faster than traditional computing for a small subset of problems. One of these is Shor’s Algorithm, which is very helpful in figuring out prime numbers, which has very important implications for cryptography. </p>
<p>As more and more research happens, more types of problems are discovered that can be solved with quantum computing. This should continue to grow over time.</p>
<p>So your next PC will not be a quantum computer, but the types and classes of problems that can be solved by Quantum Computing will continue to grow and provide real world benefits in the years ahead!</p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2016/06/WhatIsQuantumComputing/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Google I/O 2016 Recap</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/05/GoogleIO2016Recap/"/>
        <updated>2016-05-24T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2016-05-24,/2016/05/GoogleIO2016Recap/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Developer world, there are usually three big conferences each year; Microsoft’s Build, Google I/O and Apple’s World Wide Developer Conference (WWDC). Google’s <a href="https://events.google.com/io2016/">I/O</a> conference, its 10th, just wrapped up last week. Let us take a spin around some of the more interesting announcements from the conference.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/05/GoogleIO2016Recap/IO2016.jpg" alt="Google I/O 2016"> </p>
<p><strong>Google Assistant</strong> – One of the main things underlying Google I/O this year, was Artificial Intelligence. The impressive <a href="https://deepmind.com/">DeepMind</a> technology that drove <a href="https://deepmind.com/alpha-go">AlphaGo</a> to victory in March (2016) is making its way into Google’s technology. Google Assistant is really the upgrade to Google Now, making it a more conversational assistant. Similar to announcements this year from Microsoft and Facebook, bots are a huge emerging platform. Lots of tech companies definitely believe in a bot future, now it is up to consumers to see if they agree. Developers will be able to integrate with Google Assistant in the future, but no dates or APIs were announced.</p>
<p><strong>Project Ara</strong> – Ara is going to be Google’s first manufactured smartphone, remembering that whole Motorola being a separate company when Google owned it. That in itself makes it interesting and worth paying attention to. However, the Project Ara part is what makes it REALLY cool. Project Ara has 6 swappable modules on a phone, including things such as camera and speakers. However, there are many interesting use cases such as blood readers for Glucose and eInk screens. Consumers will be easily able to swap and upgrade their phone components. So if you want the best possible camera, you will be able to buy a module and swap it in. Really want great sounding music on your phone, buy a better speaker. Wired has a great <a href="http://www.wired.com/2016/05/project-ara-lives-googles-modular-phone-is-ready/">write-up</a> on Google’s vision.</p>
<p><strong>Google Home</strong> – Google announced their me too competitor to Amazon’s Alexa, a voice activated search appliance for the home. You will be able to ask Google Home things like what is the weather for the day, did the Chicago Fire win last night, etc. Pricing and availability dates were not announced. Google’s introduction video.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ro5Bvy1nf_I" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>TensorFlow</strong> – This may be, long term, the most impactful of Google’s announcements during I/O. TensorFlow is Google’s machine learning platform that was opened source late last year. At I/O, Google showed the specialty hardware they have created, called tensor processing unit (TPU) that will enable massive improvements in performance when compared to power consumption versus other platforms. If TPUs can be easily consumed via programming in a cost efficient mechanism, it could see a huge increase in use cases for machine learning.</p>
<p><strong>DayDream</strong> – Google’s VERY low cost Google Cardboard hardware provides a cheap entry to Virtual Reality. Everyone from <a href="http://www.starwars.com/games-apps/star-wars-app">Star Wars</a> to the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.im360nytvr&amp;hl=en_GB">New York Times</a> has created VR apps for the platform. DayDream appears to be the spiritual, and more ambitious, successor to Cardboard, a new virtual reality platform. DayDream will enable special phones running Android N to use VR headset to make compelling VR experiences. It appears to be similar to Samsung or Oculus approaches. Again, no date or APIs were announced. You can see the introduction video on.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ug6LSaJAO8o" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p><strong>Android N</strong> – The next version of Google’s flagship Android OS was released and is currently in Beta 3. Android N should be available, with new hardware, this fall. Google is also asking for help with the name, so if you would like to name Google N, head here. Mostly, I wonder why they haven’t doubled down on Nutella yet….</p>
<p><strong>Allo/Duo</strong> – Google added to its already long list of messaging applications with two new messaging platforms; Allo and Duo. Allo can be seen as a showcase for the upcoming Google Assistant platform, where interaction with Bots can make for a more purposeful interaction. Duo, is a video chat application (think FaceTime) that includes a feature called Knock-Knock, which allows you to see the video conversation as it starts, before answering it. Neither of these applications require a Google Account, just a phone number. However, they enter a VERY crowded field which includes WhatsApp, Facebook Messenger, etc. Not sure how much traction Google will be able to attain, unless they are made the default apps for Android N devices.</p>
<p>In general, to highlight Google’s message this year at I/O, I believe it is doubling down on the computational power that Google’s Cloud can deliver. Tensor flow, Google Assistant and Google Home are showing where the world is heading when our Smartphones are peaking, at least in terms of features. 
The other thing, is that Google, like Microsoft, is trying to move quickly, and a lot of things that were announced are not ready yet. This is markedly different from previous Google I/O conferences.
There is a land rush out there for using AI to power consumer experiences on the phone and Facebook, Microsoft and Google are rushing to claim it. It will be interesting to see Apple’s take next month at WDDC since Apple tends to be a much better hardware company than software company.
Google has made the I/O conference available for all to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XC9DNYLWvK0">watch</a>.</p>
<p>This blog post originally appeared at <a href="https://www.skylinetechnologies.com/Insights/Skyline-Blog/May_2016/Google_I_O_2016_Recap">Skyline Technologies</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2016/05/GoogleIO2016Recap/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>The Death of Moore's Law and the Game of Go</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/05/DeathOfMooresLawAndTheGameOfGo/"/>
        <updated>2016-05-03T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2016-05-03,/2016/05/DeathOfMooresLawAndTheGameOfGo/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the last 50 years or so, the land of computers has been ruled by Moore’s Law, but that time is coming to an end. </p>
<p>TLDR; Moore’s Law is dying, but instead of going smaller with transistors for computing power, we will go large with scale, AI and quantum computer for computing power</p>
<p>For those of you unfamiliar with Moore’s Law, it was an observation made in the 1960s by Gordon Moore, that the number of transistors in an integrated circuit would double approximately every two years. Moore, who went on to form Intel, was quite prescient in this declaration. </p>
<p>Intel released its first chip in 1971 and it contained approximately 2300 transistors. Fast forward to today, where a quad core Skylake chip from Intel has approximately 1.75 billion transistors. Obviously, the last 45 years has seen amazing gains in the engineering and the manufacturing processes involved in making chips for computing devices, so much so, the supercomputers of 30 years ago are the $500 smartphones we carry in our pockets.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/05/DeathOfMooresLawAndTheGameOfGo/mooresLaw.svg?raw=true" alt="Moore&apos;s Law"> source: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore%27s_law#/media/File:Transistor_Count_and_Moore%27s_Law_-_2011.svg">Wikipedia</a></p>
<p>This growth in chip size has transformed our world. Between the rise of computers, then smartphones and high speed data networks, the world is a different place. Communication costs have plummeted. We are more connected globally than ever before. Opportunities have expanded globally for millions and millions of people.  The economic and social benefits of this have been tremendous. It has been breathtaking in the scope of impact it has had on society; from the inane tweets of Kardashians to the Arab spring.</p>
<p>So Moore’s Law has been a huge success, however, it is more of an observation than a physical law. For example, Newton’s Law of Gravity is (almost always) the law of the Universe with F = ma. Moore’s Law though is not that, and its time is coming to an end. The amazing advances in the reduction of chip size will soon be a thing of the past. Without Moore’s Law, which helped create the economic engine of the Information age, does that mean GDP growth will be disappearing? Of course not, at least in terms of computing power. Instead of Moore’s law being about doubling of transistors on a chip, we now think of computation growth coming from other places. First off, to the ancient game of Go!</p>
<p>The game of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Go_%28game%29">Go</a> is a 2500-year-old game from China that is played with black and white stones on a 19x19 grid. The game has relatively simple rules, but the size of the board makes it an exceedingly complex game. While games like Chess are complex, the pieces have limited moves and varying strength, so it is somewhat easier to determine the relative value of certain moves and use brute force computation to analyze all the possible outcomes on the, relatively smaller, 8x8 chess board. In Go, the moves are much more nuanced, and players take years and years of playing, to recognize patterns to be a successful player. In computer terms, chess is a solvable problem by applying computation as demonstrated by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_Blue_%28chess_computer%29">Deep Blue</a> back in the 90s when world Chess champion Gary Kasparov was (nerd) famously beat. </p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/05/DeathOfMooresLawAndTheGameOfGo/GoGame.jpg" alt="Go Game"></p>
<p>The approach used by Deep Blue though, wouldn’t work with Go, so it has always been considered an artificial intelligence problem, more than a CPU intensive problem. The ability to beat the Go equivalent of a grandmaster was thought to be at least a decade away. So this March (2016), much of the computer world, was amazed then to see Google’s <a href="https://deepmind.com/alpha-go">AlphaGo</a> (developed by Google <a href="https://deepmind.com/">DeepMind</a>) beat a Korean champion Lee Se-Dol in a 5 game battle. You can read about the matches at <a href="http://www.theverge.com/google-deepmind">The Verge</a>. </p>
<p>We learn two things from this… First, we can replace the previous decades of massive growth of transistors on a chip with the massive growth of computing resources at scale. Google’s DeepMind program utilized a cluster of computers to derive massive computational resources to solving a very difficult problem. As connectivity becomes more pervasive and network speed grow, these computing resources can be used to solve complex problems, without needing more CPU resources on our devices.</p>
<p>The second thing we learn from Google’s DeepMind victory against a Go champion is that there are other solutions to problems. While computing power could win a game of chess, it would never win at something like Go. Instead of the brute force approach that was so effective for Deep Blue, different solutions were needed. Many years of research came to fruition, including pattern recognition, deep learning and neural networks that were bundled into DeepMind. The AlphaGo program was taught to learn by “watching” old Go games from champions, and then constantly playing itself. The more it learned, the better it became. So much so, that during the actual tournament, commentators were shocked by some of the moves the AI made, and there was one move the human player was so taken aback by, he took a very long break. This kind of growth in alternative approaches to problem solving can again, provide greater computational power while not increasing transistor size.</p>
<p>Last, another future path to computation growth is quantum computing. Quantum computing requires a bit of a deeper dive (future blog post!), but suffice to say, the world of qbits and superposition principle provides orders and orders of magnitude increases in speed for some computational cases.</p>
<p>So…. Moore’s law is going away. We are reaching the literal physical limitations of how much closer we can put transistors on a chip. We are also moving to a world where lower power usage, which equates to less chip performance is much more preferred than previous decades. This all means different computing platforms will help a variations of Moore’s law continue, where computing power continues to increase, but it will be distributed into massive scale cloud infrastructure with novel approaches like neural networks and quantum computing coupled with speedy networks to make sure today’s super computers are in our pockets in 30 years.</p>
<p>This blog post originally appeared at <a href="http://www.skylinetechnologies.com/Insights/Skyline-Blog/May_2016/Death_of_Moore_s_Law">Skyline Technologies</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2016/05/DeathOfMooresLawAndTheGameOfGo/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Build 2016 Recap</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/04/Build2016Recap/"/>
        <updated>2016-04-06T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2016-04-06,/2016/04/Build2016Recap/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Microsoft’s recent developer conference, Build, finished up last week in San Francisco. Every year, Skyline sends a team of people to Build to understand Microsoft’s direction for our customers in the coming year  </p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/04/Build2016Recap/build1.jpg" alt="Build Banner"></p>
<p>Here are some of the key takeaways</p>
<p><strong>Xamarin</strong> – Microsoft recently closed their purchase of Xamarin, a toolset for developing cross platform mobile applications across Windows, iOS and Android. The big news out of Build was that Microsoft was making the Xamarin tooling free for everyone. While free is great news, Microsoft also announced they were open sourcing Xamarin. This should encourage organizations who were hesitant about Xamarin because of cost constraints to re-evaluate!</p>
<p><strong>BASH</strong> – Microsoft is bringing the Bash Shell to Windows! This may not mean anything to a lot of folks, but to developers, it is a huge deal. The Bash Shell is the most popular Unix shell, which is the command line interface (CLI) developers use. With a lot of Open Source tooling, it was always a source of friction between how development would work on Windows vs OS X or Linux. With Microsoft teaming up with Canonical, the maker of the popular Ubuntu Linux distribution, to bring Bash to Windows this should make developing applications for multiple platforms on Windows much easier!</p>
<p><strong>Bots</strong> – One of the more interesting reveals at Build this year was the release of the Microsoft Bot platform 
(<a href="https://dev.botframework.com/">https://dev.botframework.com/</a>). Bots are really mini pieces of functionality done in an interactive environment. For example, you could create a bot to show movie times. Another bot may be able to show you bus times. The impetus for this is really two fold. First, Microsoft feels people are at peak app, which is the idea that users have so many apps, they aren’t downloading more. Does someone really need to download an app to get a bus schedule they need once or twice a year? Microsoft thinks Bots answer that question.</p>
<p><strong>Cognitive Services</strong> – The second piece of the Bot strategy is Microsoft’s introduction of Cognitive Services (<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/cognitive-services">https://www.microsoft.com/cognitive-services</a>). This is a way of bringing intelligence into applications and is the evolvement of Project Oxford via an API. Microsoft has several of these “intelligence” APIs for things such as natural language query, image recognition, etc. One example of this is an application and website that Microsoft created where you can upload a picture to the Azure cloud of a person, and have it use the AI backend Microsoft has created to tell you how old the person is (<a href="https://how-old.net/">https://how-old.net/</a>).</p>
<p><strong>Conversational UX</strong> – By combing Microsoft’s Bot strategy and cognitive services together, they are ultimately trying to create a new User Experience, via conversations. This is where you can interact with a service via your voice or typing and have it perform actions. An example shown during the keynote was ordering a pizza from Dominos via a bot you were interacting with on Skype. </p>
<p><strong>HoloLens</strong> – Microsoft officially celebrated their release of HoloLens, their impressive augmented reality headset during the first day keynote, in an oddly stilted demonstration of HoloLens. It will be a bit before we are all playing Minecraft in our living rooms via HoloLens, but the technology is shipping to devs now and it is impressive. Most of the initial applications appear to be focused on education and the enterprise, especially engineering and manufacturing scenarios. </p>
<p>One of the impressive demos of HoloLens to attendees was a NASA/Microsoft created demo of going to the surface of Mars. Using photos from Nasa rovers, a 3D environment was created that enabled attendees to look and walk around the surface of Mars. Very cool demonstration of the potential!</p>
<p><strong>New Windows</strong> – Microsoft discussed bits and pieces of the upcoming release of Windows this summer, Windows Anniversary edition, which was previously codenamed Redstone. While there wasn’t a ton of information about Redstone, the Start Menu is being evolved, Live Tiles are getting richer and better notifications are coming to the platform. Further, the Edge browser is getting new features including the ability to have extensions (yeah!).</p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/04/Build2016Recap/build2.jpg" alt="Satya Nadella Keynote"></p>
<p>Build this year was an interesting one. Microsoft, after many years of trying to get folks behind their mobile plans essentially decided to jump past mobile and envision what is after mobile. Some of their ideas include augmented reality with HoloLens as well as new ways for user to interact and do their job, via conversation with intelligent agents. When you look at the inclusion of the Bash shell and giving all developers the ability to create mobile apps for free for all platforms using C#, and you know you are dealing with a different Microsoft, a more open and diverse computing company. This is exciting to see for developers and organizations and opens both to many new and interesting opportunities.</p>
<p>This post originally appeared at <a href="http://www.skylinetechnologies.com/Insights/Skyline-Blog/April_2016/Build_2016_Recap">Skyline Technologies</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2016/04/Build2016Recap/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>NEWDUG 2016 CodeCamp - Gulp All The Things</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2016/03/newdug-codecamp-2016/"/>
        <updated>2016-03-13T06:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2016-03-13,/2016/03/newdug-codecamp-2016/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to everyone who came to my presentation at <a href="http://newcodecamp.com/">NEWDUG 2016</a> this year!
I am always appreciative of the great tech talent we have in NorthEast Wisconsin, and it was certainly evident
with the number of attendees and the quality of the presentations.</p>
<p>If you are interested, the code from the presentation is available on <a href="https://github.com/jptacek/NewDug2016">GitHub</a>.
The PowerPoint presention is also available on <a href="https://github.com/jptacek/NewDug2016/blob/master/PPT/GulpAllTheThings.pptx?raw=true">GitHub</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2016/03/newdug-codecamp-2016/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Google I/O and the Death of the Web</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2015/06/GoogleIOAndDeathOfWeb/"/>
        <updated>2015-06-01T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2015-06-01,/2015/06/GoogleIOAndDeathOfWeb/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Google recently wrapped up their annual developer conference, 
<a href="https://events.google.com/io2015/#">Google I/O</a>, and I was struck by how very 
little was said about the Web during the keynote. While the death of the web may be 
a bit of click bait title, the 2015 Google I/O conference highlights it is an app world now 
and a connected world is on the way. 
We can
start to envision a future where we use a Web Browser as much as we use a VHS player. </p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2015/06/GoogleIOAndDeathOfWeb/io15-color.png" alt="Google I/O Logo"></p>
<p>To provide some background, Google I/O is a developer conference where Google reaches out to get 
developers excited
about their platform. Microsoft has their <a href="http://www.buildwindows.com/">Build</a> 
conference  and Apple has <a href="http://www.buildwindows.com/">WWDC</a> and they all do the same
thing; encourage developers to create great things on their respective platforms and show their vision of
the future and why developers should invest their time in adopting this vision. </p>
<p>The Google we know today, with its $350 Billion (USD) market capitalization and $48 
billion (USD) in cash reserves, is a result of building great tools for the Web 
such as <a href="https://www.google.com">search</a> and <a href="https://www.gmail.com">Gmail</a>. 
Google also has many great web technologies that developers use every day.<br><a href="https://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a> is an exceedingly popular JavaScript framework.
<a href="https://cloud.google.com/appengine/docs">Google App Engine</a> is a popular cloud 
Platform As A Service (PAAS) service offering. <a href="https://www.google.com/analytics">Google Analytics</a> 
is embedded on nearly every 
web page on the Internet. <a href="http://maps.google.com/">Google Maps</a> are displayed 
on millions of web pages across the 
Internet. Google Ad Sense is responsible for the vast majority of Google&#39;s 
$48 billion cash hoard. Even tools like Google Chart are used every day by millions.</p>
<p>So how many of these apps or services were mentioned during Google&#39;s I/O keynote. Nary 
a one, despite the wide adoption and support these tools/apps have. 
The biggest web technology Google focused on during their keynote was 
<a href="https://www.polymer-project.org/1.0/">Polymer</a>, a web toolkit based on their
Material design standard that was released at the conference. Their was also the release of 
<a href="https://photos.google.com">Google Photos</a>, but that is
more about capturing the images you take on your phone than the next great Web thing.
Google used its developer conference to discuss very little of its web technologies.</p>
<p>What does this all mean? Google&#39;s mantra as of late has been the next billion users, 
and those users aren&#39;t 
coming from the web. They are coming for mobile devices, TV watchers and even cars. 
Google
is racing towards a world where all devices are connected, and they want to be there
first. Self driving cars are impressive technology, but they are also rolling data 
collectors that tell Google more about you and the world around you than your phone 
currently does. Android users in emerging economies will never own a PC and will
experience the Internet through devices and apps instead of the web. Chromecast devices
tell Google what media you like to consume. All of this data feeds to Google and 
provides data and context, which tells Google more about us and the world, all in order to 
serve up ads to 
sell you tickets to go see Ant Man.</p>
<p>Google and Apple are very well entrenched in the mobile world. However, they come from 
very different places. Google wants context and information about you, and they store
it in their massively scalable cloud. For you to give this to them, they provide much of 
these services for free. 
Apple wants to create amazing devices and 
experiences for users, charge you a premium for it and have you keep coming back. Nothing illustrates the 
difference in thought between these two companies than their photo strategy. Google
wants everything you can give it, and you can have it for free. Apple gives you a paltry
5 GB for photo storage and then wants you to pay.</p>
<p>However, the next massive area for tech growth is a world 
where everything is connected and Google is winning.
Apple is not ready to play in that world, and I haven&#39;t seen anything to indicate
they are planning to. They do not have their own scalable cloud infrastructure in place, 
though they are working on it, but it is for their services, not for developers to utilize in creating 
applications. Their
development tools are focused on selling hardware devices, not cloud. They are capturing  context
with iBeacons and iPhones, but not to the scale of Google, where it permeates Android.</p>
<p>Google is exceptionally well prepared to be ready for the connected world, it is in their
DNA to do massive scale and be a little bit creepy in what they capture about users. 
They are also creating and or buying companies that feed
data to this connected world. Nest thermostats, self driving cars, Android all feed
data and context to Google.</p>
<p>Who is going to compete with Goolge? One option is  Microsoft. 
They have lost mobile, but they are positioned to execute in a connected
world, with their Azure service for scale, and their Internet of Things strategy. However,
unlike Google, they aren&#39;t building the connected devices like Android, Android Wear,
automobiles that consumers want and will feed data and context. Microsoft is also more of an Enterprise
company these days than a consumer company, though they are working to move the bar.</p>
<p>Or maybe it is Amazon that will be there to fight Google for market share. They have the leading cloud 
service so they can do scale. Their shopping service provides context. However, their disastrous 
Fire launch indicates mobile will not be an option for providing data and context. Their focus on growth
in shopping does not provide the cash that Apple, Google and Microsoft have to buy share.</p>
<p>The web browser is now hitting the Grandparent stage of life, having begat a mobile 
world and we are seeing the start of a connected world. It has been a great ride for the web. Google and Apple
own the mobile world. The
question is who else is going to be battling with Google for the connected world?</p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2015/06/GoogleIOAndDeathOfWeb/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <title>NEWDUG 2015 CodeCamp - Getting Ready for VS 2015 By Loving the Command Prompt</title>
        <link href="https://www.jptacek.com/2015/03/newdug-codecamp-2015/"/>
        <updated>2015-03-17T05:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <id>tag:www.jptacek.com,2015-03-17,/2015/03/newdug-codecamp-2015/</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I will be presenting at the 2015 NEWDUG CodeCamp this year. Pretty excited! The CodeCamp is for developers in
NorthEast Wisconsin (or those looking for a roadtrip) and features speakers from all over the Midwest. The CodeCamp is
March 28th and will be at the Fox Valley Technical College. You can find more information, as well as register at
<a href="http://newcodecamp.com/">http://newcodecamp.com/</a>.</p>
<p>My presentation is entitled, Getting Ready for VS 2015 By Loving the Command Prompt. We are going to look at some
of the Open Source tools that will be a big part of Visual Studio 2015. These include things platforms such as
 Bower, Yeoman, NPM,
etc. We may even do some kind of dark magic where we run a Microsoft .NET MVC app natively on a OS X, because that
is now a thing.</p>
<p>If you are in the area, come check out the talk and say hi!</p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2015/03/newdug-codecamp-2015/bower-logo.png" alt="Bower logo"></p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2015/03/newdug-codecamp-2015/chocolately.jpg" alt="Chocolately logo"></p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2015/03/newdug-codecamp-2015/npm.png" alt="npm logo"></p>
<p><img src="https://www.jptacek.com/2015/03/newdug-codecamp-2015/yeoman-logo.png" alt="Yeoman logo"></p>
]]></content>
        <foo1><![CDATA[https://www.jptacek.com/2015/03/newdug-codecamp-2015/]]></foo1>
            </entry>
    
</feed>